Roll on.
Yeah I am. I should be good.
All yours.
Screen share and all that good stuff.
Cool.
You should be able to see me.
I'm singing. So.
Yes, we can see.
You're good.
All right.
Yeah, I am Taylor Howard.
I'm currently a lecturer in the Games
and Interactive Media program
at University of Central Florida.
And a little less than a month,
like 2 or 3 weeks,
I will be an assistant professor
in the Games and Interactive media program
at University of Central Florida.
So I'm excited about that.
But today,
I'm going to do a kind of postmortem
talk of an interactive fiction game
that I made called
remaster of the Red death,
which is a interactive fiction
remake recreation of Poe's
Masque of the Red death. So.
So I'll kind of give a quick summary
of the game and the main mechanics.
I'll talk a little bit
of like a little bit about like theory
history stuff.
I'm going to talk
mostly about the design process,
kind of like from ideation
all the way to release.
Basically.
I do have some plans for future updates,
although I do feel like
this is a fully released game
at this point.
You know, it's fully fleshed out in terms
of like visuals
and mechanics and narrative
and all that kind of stuff.
But I do have some things I want to add
to it and some lessons learned
from doing the project, kind of like in a
typical postmortem style. So,
so to kind of give a summary of the game,
let me minimize
the presenters thing just in case
that's getting in the way of like visuals.
But yeah, the game is an interactive
fiction remake of The Master,
the Red death.
If you're not familiar
with that short story,
it's like a creepy gothic horror
short story about a prince.
And some, like nobles
who quarantine themselves away
from an illness
that's ravaging the land, if you like.
This is something that we all kind of
have some experience with them,
and they hold this party like a few months
in, just like masquerade ball.
And at midnight,
a weird, strange, creepy visitor shows up.
And spoilers for like, 150 year
old short story Everybody Dies.
The game itself,
you know, follows that narrative.
And so one of the potential endings
is that.
But there are also
lots of other potential endings
that you can get to and stuff like that.
I made it an
Inc., which is a scripting engine
for making choice based games.
The images I didn't create myself,
and I'll talk about that
a little bit in a minute,
but those were created in sketchbook,
which is just a mobile
based digital drawing app
that you can use on your phone,
and it's fully functional with like
art mechanics, narrative, stuff like that.
I released it on my page
about six months ago.
It was like end of January, I think.
I didn't small update like early February,
so it's been out for around six months.
So, there's a lot of major mechanics
that I'm not going to go
super deep on all of this just because
obviously I'm only so much time.
But there's like a character creation
system, there's movement systems
for the player and the Prince Prospero.
The from post story is like
one of the major characters in the game.
There's a randomly generated
secret room spoilers, which gets you to
some of the endings
that are not just getting killed by death
when deaths rose up at
midnight and kills everybody.
There's like
time and health and inventory systems.
The time system is
probably the most important
because the game keeps
track of time and midnight.
The creepy visitor shows up.
And if you haven't gotten to another
ending by then, you're going to die.
There's dialog systems, NPC favor systems.
There's like 13 different endings.
So there's a lot of major mechanics
in the game.
I guess some theory and history stuff.
What this project is partially building on
is a previous work of mine
that I think I may have talked
about at ELO. At some point.
I tried to remember like various places
where I've talked about it,
but retelling the Tell-Tale heart was a
like interactive fiction remake.
I made a growing presence also heart.
I also made that an ink.
This game is a lot more expansive
and it has visuals.
That was my previous
work was like a fully text based game.
But yeah, it's also building somewhat
on like the history of remediation
and adaptation.
And as outlined by people like Bolter
and Grayson, I'm not going to throw
a bunch of like theory quotes into this,
but I did write a paper.
So if you want some of the theory quotes
and like some more in-depth stuff on that,
I did write a paper
that should be in the proceedings,
so you can obviously check that out.
So, one of the other things I kind of
identify in the paper is like that.
This is also something
that a lot of famous works at Blit
have done in the past.
And this is not,
you know, a full, extensive list of that
or something like that.
I just tried to kind of highlight
some really famous works
that that have taken, like adaptation,
remediation, rancid approaches
like Patchwork Girl being an adaptation
of Frankenstein and The Password
of Oz, and Bronze being an adaptation
of beauty and the beast.
80 days was made by the company
that makes ink and one times
game of the Day game of the year award,
and it's an adaptation
of Around the World in 80 days.
So, but yeah,
if you want more depth on that.
Again, I wrote a paper
and obviously talk about that
a lot more in the paper and stuff. So,
so the design process for the
game, I started working on this game
almost exactly a year ago.
I want to say it was in like June,
July of 2025.
So it's like basically when I started
like ideation and working in projects
and mostly just started
with like a text monument
with some ideas in it, basically.
From there,
I basically put together
a simple mechanical prototype
and presented it at a conference called
Virtual International Conference
for the fantastic in the Arts.
It's like the virtual sister
conference to the International conference
with a fantastic in the arts.
They've been doing this
for the past few years.
And so I specifically asked for feedback
at that conference about art.
There were some things I wanted
feedback on,
but one thing I specifically wanted
to get feedback on was,
like, should the game have art?
And for context, I am not a visual artist.
So I asked that question.
Knowing that
like that would mean they generate art,
copyright free art from the internet,
or recruiting an artist, basically.
So basically changing up
my typical design process
and working with someone
to have them create art.
The feedback I got was, yes,
you should have art, basically.
So, so I recruited an artist,
which went very smoothly
because it was just my girlfriend,
and she has never done
digital art for a game before,
but I think it went really well.
Like, I'm very happy with the art that,
that she created.
And I really just gave her basically
like some very minimal technical direction
and not much else.
Like I almost all the art style
and things like that come from her.
But, I wrote most of the game's code
during that time frame.
And specifically
I'll talk about this later.
I wrote the narrative prose last, and
that's a part of my lessons learned. So,
but yeah, I released the game,
I think officially put it up on my edge
page at the end of January and then, like,
made a snow updating early February.
And it's been accepted
for like a 1.0 release of the ACM
hypertext conference in September.
So I'll be like kind of doing a 1.0
release of the game at that conference.
So all of the future updates that I'm
going to mention here on this next slide
are things that I would either have
implemented by then or have cut by then.
And really, of these three things,
there's only one of them
that I think that would get cut.
There's already in progress work
on getting art for all 13 of the endings.
One of the places where the game doesn't
have as much art is in the ending section.
And right now
Emily is working on making art basically
for all of the other games endings.
This is an in progress
image of one of the art pieces
that she's working on, which is like
for the finding the secret room
and convincing people to leave the party
with you ending basically. So,
there's I want to add a little bit
more to character creation.
Right now.
I feel like the game is fairly difficult
if you don't know how to get exactly to
some of those.
The endings, I think very likely
the ending you're going to see frequently
is death throwing up
and killing everybody at midnight.
So I want to add a little bit
to character creation
to reduce time pressure on the player,
because I just feel like it's
a little bit difficult right now.
And in particular, I'm thinking about kind
of adding some like selectable
special abilities that you can use
throughout the party to like,
you know, help reduce time
pressure and stuff like that.
The one that's the most of a stretch goal
right now is potentially music
and sound effects. This is mostly because,
a I will
definitely need to outsource that.
And very likely that will mean
getting copyright free, like music
and sound effects from the internet,
which isn't a massive problem.
Like I think that will be easy to do,
and I can obviously like credit them
appropriately and stuff like that.
The slightly more challenging thing
is limitations on
on audio.
It's very limited
in terms of audio functionality,
I guess for context, Inkwell developed
as a narrative middleware engine,
and almost all the games
they have released with ink
have used a game engine like Unity
or Unreal to handle music and SFX and all,
like all that kind of stuff.
Basically, there is limited support within
ink to like
include music and SFX and visuals
and like a web based version of the game.
And it has like a feature
called export for web
that makes like an HTML, CSS,
JSON package.
So you can make like a web
playable version of it, basically.
But the audio restrictions
are essentially one sound at a time.
So you cannot layer music or play
like SFX over music or things like that.
You pretty much are limited to playing
an audio track and playing a different
audio track,
but but not much else than that.
That luckily actually lines up
pretty well with
some of the way that the audio
was described in post story,
so it might still be doable,
but if anything gets cut,
it would be that, and probably mostly
with the justification that like
a lot of people
may be playing this on a phone
and have the sound turned off anyway,
and the sound may not be necessarily
having a fun, but, but it is something
I want to try to do and we'll see.
Like that's of those three things,
the one thing that I think I make. But
so some lessons learned
these I'm kind of basing on Chandler's
Game Production Handbook
and a lot of other people who discuss,
like doing postmortems for games,
and they almost always highlight
the value of doing like a lessons
learned as part of that.
And so I, I present these in the paper
to and talk about them
a little bit more in depth there.
So if you want like a little bit
more depth of these
obviously you can read the paper,
but one was just staying flexible
about development.
And in this particular situation, for me
that meant staying flexible
about solar development versus
working with someone else.
Because like I went into this project
assuming I would do it
the same way I did every other project
I've worked on in the past,
which was basically do something
that I can make completely myself
without having to work with anybody else,
because that gives me
like full control
over the development process.
But early on, getting the feedback that,
like, I should reconsider that was useful.
And then, you know, my lesson
kind of take away from
that is staying flexible about development
and maybe be considering some of your,
like, common conceptions about how you might approach the development process. So,
one that
I do feel pretty strongly about that.
This is a really useful piece of advice
for an interactive fiction developers.
I've given this advice to students a lot.
Is writing pros at the end,
I based this piece of advice
to some extent on a game Developers
Gain Developers
Conference talk given by Josh Sawyer
about Fallout New Vegas,
and he prevents this like five step model
for doing narrative design.
I didn't follow that five step model
except for the last step.
And the last step is right crows.
And essentially his argument is do the
majority of your narrative design first?
It will make writing the prose easier,
which was very true for me,
and it kind of plays into my third lesson,
which was make an implementation prototype
and get feedback early.
I'm borrowing the concept
of an implementation
prototype from Food and Hill in an article
called What Prototypes prototype.
Implementation prototype is essentially
a mechanics oriented prototype
like it's not pretty.
There are no esthetics
we're not worried about,
like the visuals, we're only worried
about core functionality, basically.
And doing that was really useful for me
because I got early feedback
that I should reconsider
having visuals in the
in the piece,
and that helped with the second lesson
learned that I just mentioned in that
when I started writing the prose text,
I realized, like,
I'm going to have visuals
and I do not need to spend a bunch of time
writing out visual descriptions of,
like the rooms that the party takes place
in, inside of this mansion
and stuff like that,
which all have these weird
colors and stuff.
So because those the visual images
can present that stuff and I can focus
the text more on like narrative
and things like that. So,
so that pretty much does it for me.
I want to thank everybody
for listening to me today.
If you want to play the game,
I'll drop a link in the chat as well.
But obviously you can play
the current version of it right now.
And if you want to get in touch with me,
Gmail is the easiest way to reach me
because I have a lot of students
in my classes,
and if you send an email to my UCLA email,
I probably won't see it.
Thank you very much.